在大约两亿年前
200 million years ago,
地球看起来与今天的
our planet looked very different
迥然不同
from what it does today.
在几乎完全被海洋覆盖的地球表面
It was entirely covered by sea,
仅有一片超级大陆 人称“盘古大陆”
which surrounded one single supercontinent we call Pangea.
之后盘古大陆开始分裂
And then Pangea began to break up.
于是 生命随着破碎的陆地板块
Life was cast adrift
分离漂移
on fragments of land.
这些碎裂的板块最终形成了我们如今的七大洲
And these fragments eventually became our seven continents.
我们本次即将去探索不同大陆如何形成了
We will see how life developed on each continent,
我们今天看到的各具特色
giving rise to the extraordinary and wonderful diversity
而又纷繁多样的生命
that we see today.
我们将深入冰雪覆盖的南极荒野探险
We'll venture through the frozen wilderness of Antarctica,
那里的动物们克服了极端环境 繁衍兴盛
where life thrives against the odds.
我们将探索富饶的南美洲
And to the riches of South America,
那里处处充满惊奇
full of the unexpected.
还会从野性十足的非洲荒野
From the wilds of Africa.
到北美洲的广袤土地
To the vast expanses of North America
再到炽热难耐的澳大利亚
and the searing heat of Australia.
我们将踏足亚洲的偏远角落
We'll explore the remote reaches of Asia,
寻找那些与世隔绝 难得一见的珍稀动物
home to rarely seen creatures.
我们将漫步欧洲 感受这个被人类改造的世界
And Europe, a world transformed by humanity.
我们将会发现这或许是
And we'll discover how this may be
自七大洲形成以来地球生命迎来的
the most critical moment for life on Earth
最重要时刻
since the continents formed.
我们正在快速改变世界
We are changing the world so rapidly,
而野生动物被迫面临迄今为止最严峻的挑战
that wildlife is now facing some of its greatest challenges yet.
现在到了最关键的时刻
Never has it been a more important time
展现七大洲多彩生命的任务
to reveal the precious diversity of life
变得刻不容缓
on our seven continents.
这就是七个世界 一个星球
This is Seven Worlds, One Planet.
七个世界 一个星球
在地球七大洲中
Of all the continents,
有一片大陆在大约200年前才被人类首次发现
one was first sighted by humans just 200 years ago.
直到现在
And only now
我们才得以对当地的
are we beginning to understand
生命生存状况 窥见一斑
what it takes to survive here.
这里是全球环境最恶劣的地方
It's the most hostile of them all.
南极洲
第一集
解说 大卫·爱登堡
98%的陆地被冰雪覆盖
98% of mainland Antarctica,
南极洲的陆地面积约是美国国土面积的
an area one-and-a-half times the size of the United States,
1.5倍
is covered in ice
几乎看不到任何生命迹象
on which virtually nothing can live.
动物们只能依赖四周的海洋为生
So life is dependent on the ocean that surrounds it.
但即便是海洋也会冻结
But even the ocean freezes.
只有一种哺乳动物能在这片极南之地生存
Only one mammal can live this far south.
它就是韦德尔氏海豹
The Weddell seal.
这头雌性海豹不断用牙齿
She has to keep her breathing hole open
磨蹭冰层边缘 保持呼吸孔洞的畅通
by grinding back the ice with her teeth.
在一望无际的海冰上
Out here on the sea ice,
韦德尔氏海豹可以避开来自开阔海域的捕食者袭击
all these seals are far from the predators of the open ocean.
这里俨然已经成为雌性海豹最安全的繁殖地点
So, this is the safest place for her to give birth.
海豹幼崽从温暖的子宫落到冰面上
Leaving the warmth of the womb and landing on ice
它刚刚出生就经历了最剧烈的温差变化
is the sharpest drop in temperature any animal ever faces.
糟糕的是 幼崽在出生后的前10天里不会游泳
But her pup can't swim for the first ten days of its life.
它被困在海冰上
It's trapped here
不能入水
out on the ice.
海豹妈妈用庞大的身躯为幼崽挡住寒风
She shields her pup from the wind.
现在虽然是春季 但气温可以下降到
Although in spring, temperatures can drop
零下40摄氏度
to minus 40 degrees Celsius,
强劲的暴风雪可能会持续数天
and blizzards can rage for days.
3天过去了 暴风雪还在疯狂肆虐
Three days on, and the storm is still raging.
现在海豹妈妈被迫面临最艰难的选择
She now faces the hardest of decisions.
是留下守护幼崽
Does she stay with her pup?
还是回到水中寻求庇护
Or shelter in the water?
现在这只海豹幼崽要想死里逃生
Now, her pup's best chance of survival
只能祈祷肆虐的暴风雪赶快停止
is for the storm to pass quickly.
有些幼崽没能逃过一劫
Some pups didn't make it.
呼唤得到了回应
An answer.
这只幼崽如果现在跟随妈妈一起下水
If this pup now joins its mother in the water,
就再也不用担心
it will be safe
暴风雪的侵袭了
from any future storm.
水下温度只有零下2摄氏度
It's minus two degrees Celsius,
但这总比趴在冰上
but being in water is warmer
忍受寒风呼啸
than lying on the ice
要暖和多了
in the howling wind.
幼崽的生存几率大大提高
Its chances of surviving here are now extremely good.
只有少数耐寒动物能够长年累月生活在这片极南之地
Only a few hardy animals can live all year round as far south as this.
南极洲远离极点的大陆边缘地带
further from the pole, on the fringes of the continent,
散布着许多不会结冰的岛屿
lie islands that are free of sea ice.
不过 这里存在其它挑战
Here, there are other challenges.
南乔治亚岛的圣安德鲁斯湾
St Andrews Bay on South Georgia
栖息着大约50万只王企鹅
is packed with half a million king penguins.
春季 王企鹅父母经常要
In spring, the chicks are left for days,
连续数日外出觅食
while their parents are away
只有企鹅宝宝独自留在岛上
collecting food for them.
父母们也有简单的交代
There is a simple arrangement.
幼鸟必须原地等待
The chicks must stay exactly where their parents left them
方便父母返回时找到它们
to be sure of being found again.
但是这只企鹅宝宝似乎游兴正浓
But this chick has decided to look around.
四周要探查的东西比比皆是
There is a lot to be investigated.
但它绝对不能过于远离
But it must not stray too far
与父母的会面地点
from its meeting place.
这只成年王企鹅
This parent has returned
将食物藏在嗉囊里返回
with food in its crop.
但孩子却不见踪影
But its chick isn't where it left it.
好玩的东西太多
It's hard to stay put
企鹅宝宝们很难抵挡诱惑
when there's so much to play with.
不过 这里还有象海豹做邻居
Elephant seals are here, too.
它看起来太神秘了
Very mysterious.
要在茫茫鸟海中找到自己的孩子
Finding it in the crowd of youngsters
无异于大海捞针
is not going to be easy.
它们必须通过叫声相互识别
They must recognise each other by their calls.
可是在这样喧闹不已的栖息地中
But to hear these in such a noisy colony,
只有在15米内才能互相听清对方
then they must be within 15 metres of each other.
总算团聚了
Reunited.
圣安德鲁斯海滩是地球上最拥挤的海滩之一
St Andrews Beach is one of the most crowded on the planet,
要占据一块领地必须要经过连番血战
and so holding a territory here is a constant battle.
这只雄性象海豹
This bull elephant seal holds
会与多达60只雌性进行交配
the mating rights to 60 females.
两个月来 它一直严密守护这片海滩
For two months, he's guarded this stretch of beach.
因为无暇进食
Unable to feed,
它的体重正以每天10公斤的速度锐减
he's losing ten kilos a day,
此时它早已疲惫不堪
and he's exhausted.
但还有其它雄性在海滩附近徘徊
But other bulls are lying around,
伺机而动
waiting their chance.
15厘米厚的皮下脂肪
Blubber, 15 centimetres thick,
御寒效果良好
is protection against the cold,
但是当4吨重的对手袭来时
but not from the impact
这层防护就有些微不足道了
of a four-tonne opponent.
雄性象海豹据守阵地
He holds his ground
入侵者狼狈
and forces the intruder
逃向海洋
back out to sea.
南极洲的生活其实非常艰难
Life in the Antarctic is harsh indeed.
但动物们之所以蜂拥而来
But all these creatures come here
是因为南冰洋的海水中
because the Southern Ocean
富含各种营养
is one of the richest on Earth.
大约3000万年前
When, 30 million years ago,
南极洲与南美洲分离后
the continent broke away
一路向南漂移
from South America and drifted south,
由此形成了环绕南极洲的洋流
currents began to swirl right around it.
这是现今地球上
They are now the strongest
最为强劲的洋流
of any currents on the planet.
它们从深海中卷起营养物质
They sweep up nutrients from the depths,
从而创造出世界上最丰富的
and so create one of the richest feeding grounds
海洋觅食地之一
in all the world's oceans.
有些赶来
And some of the creatures
享用美餐的动物
that come here to feast
采用了一些最复杂的捕食战略
do so in a most sophisticated way.
这是座头鲸
Humpback whales.
它们每年夏季都会前来
It's summer, and they've come here
参加盛宴
for a banquet.
寒冷的海水孕育了
The cold waters contain
浩浩荡荡的大群磷虾
great shoals of krill.
据估计磷虾的数量多达400万亿只
It's estimated that there are 400 trillion of them
而它们的重量总和超过地球上
and that their combined weight is greater than that of any other
其它任何一个物种的重量总和
animal species on the planet.
座头鲸接连吐出气泡 编织出一道
To collect them, the humpbacks blow curtains of bubbles,
磷虾无法穿越的气泡网
which the krill won't cross.
随后座头鲸向内螺旋上升 将磷虾群收拢集中
The whales then rise, spiralling inwards, to concentrate the swarm.
南极洲的夏季食物丰饶
Summer in Antarctica is a time of plenty,
大多数座头鲸能在这里获得全年所需的
when most humpbacks are able to put on the reserves they need
脂肪储备
for the whole year.
但这片水域的野生动物们变得前途未卜
But the wildlife in these waters faces an uncertain future.
南极地区的海洋温度正在上升
The Southern Ocean is warming.
南极洲汇聚了世界上90%的冰
90% of the world's ice lies in Antarctica
在某些地区冰雪消融的速度
and, in some parts, the rate at which it's melting
每十年会翻一番
is doubling every decade.
海平面正在上升
Sea levels are rising.
但这里还存在一个更直接的威胁
But there is a more immediate threat.
南极洲是地球上最寒冷的地区 气候变暖正对全球气候模式
The warming of the coldest region on Earth is having a profound effect
产生深远影响
on global weather patterns.
这里的动物们已经感受到气候变化的影响
And this change in the climate is already being felt right here.
这只灰头信天翁的雏鸟只有四个星期大
This grey-headed albatross chick is four weeks old.
它的父母轮流为雏鸟遮挡凛冽的寒风
So far, it has been sheltered from the gales by its parents,
和出海觅食
who take turns to collect food for it out at sea.
这是它们两年来孕育的唯一一只雏乌
It is the only chick that they will have in two years.
鸟喙间的轻微碰触 加强了彼此之间的纽带
The delicate touching of beaks strengthens their bond.
但是这样的温情时刻不会一直持续
But these tender moments cannot last forever.
在雏鸟渐渐长大时 它们的胃口大增
As a chick grows, so does its appetite.
灰头信天翁父母不得不相继外出捕猎
So one parent has to leave to find food before the other returns.
离别是一个重要的抉择 它们需要时间来适应
Parting is a big step and they take time over it.
这是雏鸟第一次独自面对这个世界
For the first time in its life, this chick is alone.
南极洲是风暴最多 风力最强的大陆
The Antarctic is the windiest continent,
近年来因为气候变化 暴风雨变得更加频繁
and in recent years, climate change has brought storms
威力更加强劲
that are more frequent and even more powerful.
这里狂风呼啸 风速通常可达每小时110公里
Winds now regularly reach 70mph.
灰头信天翁雏鸟必颁坚守在巢穴中
But the albatross chicks must try to stay on their nests.
雏鸟在暴风雨中幸免于难
Surviving the storm is one thing...
但是在低温下存活却是又一大挑战
..but now, off the nest in these freezing temperatures,
雏鸟一旦离开鸟巢 只能勉强存活数小时
this chick has just hours to live.
残酷的环境让它们付出了沉重代价
The brutal conditions have taken their toll.
有些雏鸟最终没能逃过这一劫难
Some chicks have already succumbed to exposure.
父子亲情如此强烈 这位灰头信天翁父亲久久不肯离去
The bond is so strong, it can be hard for a father to let go.
在过去的15年里 灰头信天翁的数量
The albatross population here has more than halved
已经减少了一半以上
in the last 15 years.
它们正面临灭绝边缘
These albatross are facing extinction.
它们根本无法适应外界变化
They simply cannot keep pace with the changes
对栖息地环境造成的影响
affecting their world.
越来越多的灰头信天翁父母返回栖息地
More parents are returning to the colony.
情况似乎不太对劲
Something is not right.
鸟巢里空空如也
The nest should not be empty.
雏鸟其实就在鸟巢下方
The chick is actually right below its parent,
但因为雏鸟没待在鸟巢里 一家人就难以相认
but because it's not on the nest, the parent doesn't recognise it.
成鸟对求助无动于衷
And doesn't help it.
这看起来或许令人费解 灰头信天翁并不是通过视觉、听觉或者嗅觉
Strangely, perhaps, these albatross do not recognise their chicks
来识别自己的孩子
by sight, sound or smell.
相反它们唯一的判断依据就是鸟巢
They identify them by finding them on the nest.
所以这些猛烈的暴风雨给整个灰头信天翁种群
So, these violent storms have created a problem
带来了一大无法解决的难题
that the albatross are not equipped to solve.
这只雏鸟要想捡回一命 就必须依靠自己的力量
If it is to survive, the chick will have to get back on the nest
爬回鸟巢
by itself.
雏鸟终于大功告成
The chick has made it.
亲情纽带迅速重建
The bond is re-established immediately
信天翁雏鸟终于从成鸟那里获得了
and its parent, once again, provides the warmth that the chick
它迫切需要的温暖
so desperately needs.
眼下它算是安全了
It's safe...for now.
南极洲并没有什么地方适宜生存
Nowhere in Antarctica is survival easy.
巴布亚企鹅每天要长途跋涉长达80公里
Gentoo penguins travel up to 50 miles every day
外出觅食
to find food.
现在 它们正要返回幼鸟身边
And they're now returning to their chicks.
它们是海洋中游泳速度最快的企鹅
They are the fastest penguin in the sea
时速可以达到35公里
and can swim at 22mph.
但是海洋中还有其它速度高手
But other animals can swim much faster.
虎鲸
Orca.
这只企鹅这能依靠敏捷逃生
This penguin must rely on its agility.
可惜在4头虎鲸的围追堵截下 它的机会过于渺茫
With four orcas chasing it, the penguin stood little chance.
大多数巴布亚企鹅设法顺利返回了栖息地
Most gentoo parents do make it back to the colony.
今天 成年企鹅收获颇丰 带回了大量磷虾
Today, it's been a good hunt for krill.
也许有些太多了
Perhaps too good.
随着幼鸟们渐渐长大 莫西干发型
The chicks grow and it seems that the Mohawk style
似乎再次流行起来
is back in fashion.
这只是暂时的
It's just a phase.
长大还会变样
He'll grow out of it.
它很快就会换掉体表残留的绒羽 然后准备离开栖息地
He'll soon lose these remaining down feathers and be ready to leave
独自外出觅食
the colony and collect food for himself.
但是因为气候变化 要做到这点变得越来越难
But doing so is becoming harder because of climate change.
这个地区的冰川大量融化崩解
Glaciers in the region are now calving faster
消融速度创出了新记录
than they have done since records began.
现在各个海湾里布满了杂乱的浮冰
And this brash ice now fills the bays.
现在是秋季
It's autumn.
这些幼鸟早已换掉稚嫩的绒羽 此刻它们饥肠辘辘
The chicks have lost their down feathers and they're hungry.
必须首次尝试出海
They must go to sea for the first time.
但下水的话 它们可能会遭到浮冰的无情碾压
But now there's a risk of being crushed between blocks of ice.
它们必须到达远处的冰山
They have to get to the distant icebergs...
然后前往遥远的广阔海洋
..and so reach the open ocean that lies beyond.
说起来容易做起来难
And that is easier said than done.
豹海豹靠近了
A leopard seal...
它们是巴布亚企鹅的天敌
..their main predator.
它体形庞大 身长约有3米
It's a giant, three metres long.
这种遍布浮冰的环境 为它的捕猎提供了便利
These icy conditions help it to hunt.
这种情况下 企鹅既不能顺利行走 也不能自由游动
The penguins can neither walk nor swim.
它们根本无法判断豹海豹会从何处发起攻击
They have no way of telling where the seal will strike.
它们成了唾手可得的美食
These are easy pickings.
有些企鹅果断选择了撤退
For some, it's time to retreat.
可是现在一切又回到了原点
But now, it's back to square one.
它别无选择 只能再次尝试突破天敌的围追堵截
There's no alternative but to run the gauntlet once again.
这只豹海豹似乎在故意逗弄猎物
The seal seems to be toying with this penguin.
而企鹅安全在望
But safety is in sight.
这块浮冰十分靠近开阔海域
The ice floe is near the open ocean.
但这只企鹅已经筋疲力尽了
But this penguin is exhausted.
也许它觉得这么做有些得不偿失
Perhaps it's not worth it, after all.
冬季即将来临
Winter is coming.
南极洲正在经历一场巨变
Antarctica now undergoes a major transformation.
每天都有10万多平方公里的海洋变成冰封之地
Every day, 40,000 more square miles of sea freeze over.
到了冬末 南极洲的冰面面积整个翻了一倍
By the end of winter, the continent has doubled in size.
这是目前世界上最大的白色荒漠
This is by far the largest desert in the world.
不过在冰封的海面之下 隐藏着一个巨大的秘密
But the frozen surface of the sea hides a great secret.
冰面上的环境极端恶劣 但冰面之下的
It may be hostile above the ice, but below it,
生存环境相对稳定 这里的海洋生命历经数千年的岁月变迁
conditions are so stable that life over millennia
物种纷繁多样
has had time to diversify.
许多生物进化出庞大的体形
Creatures here grow to a great size.
这些四处觅食的纽虫足有3米长
Predatory nemertean worms are three metres long.
快进后我们才得以欣赏到它们的演出
These dramas only become visible when speeded up.
对于这些奇特的生物 我们才刚刚开始探究
We're only just beginning to discover the details of the lives
它们的生活细节
of such strange creatures.
海蛞蝓是雌雄同体的动物
Nudibranchs are hermaphrodites.
每只海蛞蝓各有一套雄性和雌性生殖器官
Each individual possesses both male and female reproductive organs.
它们交配时 只需再找到一只同类
So, to mate, one nudibranch just needs to find
任何个体都可以
And any one will do.
问题是 它们的眼睛几乎看不到物体 所以找寻同类也并非易事
But nonetheless, this is a challenge when their tiny eyes can barely see.
有些海蛞蝓的运气不错
Some do get lucky.
它们相互进行异体授精 可以各自繁殖出后代
They're fertilising each other and both will produce young.
当连同类都难寻时 交配无需分辨性别的做法
When it's hard to find a partner, it pays not to have to worry
确实大有益处
about your gender.
海葵看起来或许很像植物 其实却是不折不扣的动物
Sea anemones may look like plants, but, actually, are animals
它四处伸展触手 捕食水流中
and feed by catching edible particles that drift within reach
漂浮的可食物质
of their tentacles.
不过扎根海底意味着它们很容易遭到捕食者攻击
But being rooted to the sea floor makes them vulnerable to predators.
一种直径大约一米的远洋水母正在四处觅食
An ocean-going jellyfish, a metre or so across, searching for food.
这只水母察觉到了猎物
The jellyfish senses prey.
但是水母捕猎不成 反倒被海葵们降服
But it's the sea anemones that have made the catch
它们捕获了一只大怪物
and they've grabbed a monster.
这些捕食者守株待免 便获得了一顿大餐
A rare feast for these stationary predators.
在接下来的4天里 它们可以慢慢消化了
They devour their catch over the next four days.
数千年来 冰层下的海洋生命几乎毫无改变
Life here under the ice has remained unchanged for millennia.
但是在过去的200年里 南极洲的许多野生动物
But in the last 200 years, much of Antarctica's wildlife
不得不面临一些新到的捕食者
has had to face new predators...
人类
..human beings.
我们人类发明了新的捕猎技巧 并毫不留情地捕杀海洋生物
We devised new hunting techniques and used them so mercilessly
险些导致巨型鲸类销声匿迹
that we almost exterminated the great whales.
南乔治亚岛的这些捕鲸站曾是
These whaling stations on South Georgia were at the centre
捕鲸行业的中心
of this industry.
单纯南极海域就有超过150万头鲸鱼
More than one-and-a-half million whales were slaughtered
相继遭到猎杀
in Antarctic waters.
人们从它们庞大的身躯上剥下厚厚的脂肪
The blubber was stripped from their massive bodies
放入大桶中 熬煮制造人造黄油和肥皂
and boiled down in vats to make margarine and soap.
目前记载的最大的一头蓝鲸
And the largest animal ever recorded,
体长33米 寿命超过100岁
a 33-metre blue whale, perhaps over 100 years old,
它在短短两小时内就在这里惨遭肢解
was butchered on this ramp in just two hours.
这种肆无忌惮的屠杀行为标志着人类与自然世界的关系
This reckless slaughter marked a new low in our relationship
跌至新低
with the natural world.
南露脊鲸受到的打击最为严重
Southern right whales were hit the hardest.
它们生性好奇 毫无戒心
They were so trusting and inquisitive
经常会主动靠近捕鲸船
that they swam right up to the whalers' boats.
捕鲸者认为它们很不错
And the whalers called them right whales
就是因为它们很方便猎杀
because they were the right whales to hunt.
带着幼崽的南露脊鲸是捕鲸者最先攻击的目标
Mothers with calves were targeted first.
雌性南露脊鲸通常到相同的避风港繁殖后代
To give birth, females came to the same sheltered bays
而且会与幼崽始终形影不离
and would not leave their calves alone at the surface.
短短几十年里 就有3.5万头南露脊鲸遭到猎杀
In just decades, a population of 35,000
仅剩35头雌性南露脊鲸存活下来
was so reduced that only 35 of the females survived.
好在局面发生了转变
But times have changed.
1986年国际捕鲸委员会通过法令禁止商业捕鲸
A ban on the commercial hunting of whales, introduced in 1986,
只有日本、挪威和冰岛除外
has stopped all but Japan, Norway and Iceland.
我们与这些非凡动物的关系
Our relationship to these remarkable creatures
得以显著改善
has undergone a huge shift.
如今科学家们对南露脊鲸已有了很多了解
Scientists are now learning a great deal about these whales.
但它们的寿命仍旧是个谜
But we still don't know how long they live.
有人认为现存的这些南露脊鲸
It's thought that some individuals alive today
很可能也经历过那些捕鲸猖撅的年代
were around at the time of the mass slaughter.
尽管如此 这些60吨重的庞然大物
Yet these 60-tonne whales remain gentle
对人类仍旧保持着温和和好奇的态度
and inquisitive around humans.
随着商业捕鲸的禁止
By putting a stop to commercial hunting,
南露脊鲸的种群数量已经达到了2000多头
this population of whales has now grown to over 2,000.
这种庞然大物在南极水域的种群恢复
The recovery of life in Antarctic waters may have a significance
将会产生深远影响 不仅仅局限于南极大陆
that extends far beyond the reaches of the continent
甚至会影响我们整个人类
and will affect us all.
就在南极洲的象岛海岸
Just off the coast of Elephant Island,
我们最近目睹了
we have recently witnessed what might be
地球上最蔚为壮观的觅食景象
the greatest feeding spectacle on Earth.
在遥远的地平线上 150多条鲸鱼聚在一起
On the horizon, over 150 whales have gathered
尽情享受着难得的磷虾盛宴
to feast on krill.
又是迄今为止拍到的世界上规模最大的鲸鱼集会
This is the largest congregation of great whales ever filmed.
它们中大多数是长须鲸 体长将近26米
These are mostly fin whales, up to 26 metres long.
座头鲸在它面前都有些相形见绌了
Humpback whales are dwarfed in comparison.
来自南极海域的成千上万只动物
Thousands of animals from all over Antarctic waters
正在向这里进发
are making their way here.
这片广阔的海洋再次变得生机勃勃
These seas are, once again, beginning to brim with life.
科学家们发现南极附近海域
And scientists have discovered that the Southern Ocean,
及其孕育的无数生命吸收大气中碳元素的含量
and the life within it, soaks up more than twice as much
是亚马孙雨林吸收量的两倍还多
carbon from the atmosphere as the Amazon rainforest.
通过保护南极洲 我们不仅能够保护这里多样的生命
By protecting Antarctica, we don't just protect the life here...
也有助于恢复我们整个星球的
..we are helping to restore the natural balance
自然平衡
of the entire planet.
南极洲拍摄幕后
圣安德鲁斯湾是见证南极洲最壮观奇景的
St Andrews Bay provides one of the most spectacular sights
绝佳所在
in the whole of the Antarctic.
但是要到达那里 摄制组必须穿越
But to get there, the team will have to cross
世界上最狂暴的海洋 紧张情绪显而易见
the roughest seas in the world, and nerves are starting to show.
罗尔夫·斯坦曼 摄影师
现在风已经越来越大了
The wind is picking up already!
摄制组要在海上航行10天 才能到达偏远的圣安德鲁斯湾
It'll take ten days at sea to reach this remote location.
但是很快 他们就开始受到晕船的困扰
And it's not long before they start to feel a bit green.
有大浪涌过来了
There's some big waves coming now.
马克·麦克埃文 摄影师
鉴于这种情况要持续数天时间 摄制组人员选择轮流驾驶的方式
With these conditions lasting days, all who can take shifts at the helm.
说实话 如果你现在掉进水里
And you get given a talk, to say if you fall in the water here,
其他人完全无能为力 他们根本救不了你
there's nothing anyone can do - they can't save you.
太冷了 只要在水里待几分钟就会没命
It's so cold, you'll die in under a couple of minutes.
在甲板下面 饱受晕船之苦的罗尔夫仍旧无法站立
Below deck, Rolf hasn't yet found his sea legs.
我感觉坐船就像接受惩罚 或者被囚禁了一样
For me, this is like punishment or prisoner-ship or whatever.
真是搞不明白 怎么还有人主动要这么做
I mean, I can't understand at all how people do this voluntarily,
居然还有人梦想坐船或者航海什么的
people dream of being on a boat or sailing or anything.
仔细看看
Look at that.
我是说船不停地上下颤簸
I mean, look how much the boat is moving.
感觉就像在洗衣机里一样
I feel like in a washing machine.
南乔治亚岛终于出现在他们的正前方
The island of South Georgia finally appears.
踏上坚实的陆地让人如释重负
It's a relief to step onto solid land.
没错 说实话我已经忘记晕船的事了
Yeah, the seasickness is already forgotten, to be honest!
早就抛到脑后了
But it's all forgotten.
这地方真是不可思议
It's just out of this world.
看到地球上还有这种地方实在太棒了
It's so wonderful that these places still exist.
他们将在圣安德鲁斯湾拍摄3周
They will spend the next three weeks in St Andrews Bay.
罗尔夫的主要任务是拍摄这个巨型栖息地里的王企鹅
Rolf is here to film the king penguins in this enormous colony.
而马克必须拍摄象海豹狂暴血腥的交配季节
And Mark must capture the elephant seals' intense mating season.
在拥挤的海滩上 战争随时可能爆发
On such a crowded beach, fights can break out anywhere.
雄性象海豹体长将近6米
Males are up to six metres long and they are pumped
体内充满睾丸激素
full of testosterone.
它们对摄影师熟视无睹 行动起来横冲直撞
The bulls take little notice of the crew and will stop at nothing.
我的天呐
Oh, my God!
刚才还什么都没有 一下子就冲过来
That went from nothing to being nearly steam-rollered
四头雄性
by four huge males.
远离海滩的喧嚣和混乱 罗尔夫拍摄着眼前的王企鹅
Beyond the chaos of the beach, Rolf has king penguins in front of him,
谢天谢地 他又露出了笑脸
and, thankfully, he's smiling again.
我真的觉得应该叫它们“绅士企鹅”
I would really call them the gentleman penguins
因为它们很有礼貌 很有魅力
because they are very polite, they're charming,
很幽默
they have humour.
它们有许多搞笑有趣的瞬间
There's so many funny, lovely moments.
就这点来说我真的很喜欢它们
I absolutely adore these penguins for that!
但几周相处下来 与企鹅群共同生活的弊端
But as weeks go by, the reality of living amongst penguins
开始显露无疑
comes to the fore.
每天早上我都在想 臭死了
Every morning, I think, "Wow, it's stinky!"
但后来我才意识到 臭味是从我的鞋子还有我身上
But then I realise, these smells come out of my shoes
散发出来的
and it's myself.
在海滩上 摄影师用到了摄影机稳定器
Back on the beach, the team is using a stabilised camera rig.
以便在拍摄打斗画面时快速反应
They can now react faster to fights.
到目前为止 我们只看到许多快速打斗
So far in the shoot, we've seen a lot of quick fights,
还没有看到一头雄性
but we haven't seen some extended fights,
跟另一头雄性的
where you see one bull paired
实力对抗
equally against another bull.
象海豹的打斗场面很罕见
These sights are rare.
他们必须时刻准备
The team will need to be at the ready.
马克 马克 马克
Mark, Mark, Mark!
我们得赶快跑
Let's get running.
哦 你好
Oh, hello!
这两头雄性的实力差不多
These are two huge, evenly matched boys.
我知道
I know.
- 我从未想过能离它们这么近  - 是啊 我也没想到
Wow, I never thought we'd be this close to it. I know, nor did I.
这实在太激烈了 我们得当心点
This is really tense, we've just got to watch out.
拍到了
We got there.
我从来没想到能离得这么近
I never thought I'd see it that close
而且还能四处活动 它们就像是
and be able to move around it, as this kind of
在表演狂暴的芭蕾舞
aggressive ballet is happening.
这确实会让你很紧张
And it does make you quite tense.
拍摄进展一切顺利 但是摄制组人员注意到一些令人担忧的迹象
The shoot is going well, but the crew are noticing worrying signs.
今天的天气真的很热
It's a really hot day today.
30年前那 座冰川的前缘
30 years ago, the front of that glacier
就在那边的海滩位置
was right down on the beach.
现在后退了很远
It's retreated a huge amount.
我真的不知道气候变化会对所有这些动物
I don't really know what climate change is going to mean
产生怎样的影响
for all the wildlife that's living here.
在南极洲的部分地区 气候变暖的速度
Parts of the Antarctic are warming five times faster
是世界其它地区的5倍
than the rest of the world.
如果这一趋势持续下去 所有极地生物的处境
If this trend continues, it will threaten the very existence
都将岌岌可危
of these polar creatures.
在拍摄的最后一天 摄制组成员不禁开始思考
On the last day of filming, the team can't help but reflect
当地野生动物的未来
on the future of the wildlife here.
我内心真的很激动 因为我知道这可能是我这辈子
For me, it's emotional because I know this might have been
唯一的一次经历
a once-in-a-lifetime experience.
这里给我留下了许多美好回忆 同时我很难过
I will definitely take big memories with me and I will be sad.
这地方真的很特别 我
It's a really special place, you know? So...
不知道怎样去说
I don't know.
我只希望我们能留住这些地方
I just hope we can keep these places.
并保护好它们
And protect them.
下集预告
Next time...
地球上最大洲
..the largest continent on Earth.
一个遍布极端环境的世界
A world of extremes...
极其罕见的动物漫步其间
..where rarely seen animals roam the land...
亚洲
..Asia.